<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3822" status="New">
<title>Avoiding normalization in <tt>filesystem::weakly_canonical</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[fs.op.weakly.canonical]"/></section>
<submitter>US</submitter>
<date>08 Nov 2022</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
This addresses NB comment
<b><a href="https://github.com/cplusplus/nbballot/issues/448">US-60-125</a></b>
(<sref ref="[fs.op.weakly.canonical]"/> Avoiding normalization)
</p>

<p>
NB comment: "Implementations cannot avoid normalization because arbitrary file system changes may have occurred since any previous call. Proposed change:
Remove the paragraph."
</p>

<note>Kona 2022-11-07; LWG review</note>
<p>
Discussion revolved around two different interpretations of the <i>Remarks</i>:
<ul>
<li>
It's normative recommendation for <tt>path</tt> objects to cache some kind of
flag that indicates they are in a normalized form, which would be checked in
<tt>weakly_canonical</tt> to avoid normalizing again. This is the interpretation
assumed by the NB comment, which correctly notes that such caching would be
unreliable.
</li>
<li>
It's an optimization hint to implementors that they should not normalize the
result if each component has been canonicalized one-by-one. That is, when
canonicalizing <tt>"/a/b/c"</tt> by incrementally building up canonicalized 
components, if the entire path exists then the result will already have been
normalized and should not be normalized again explicitly.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
For the first interpretation, the recommendation is a bad recommendation and
should be removed as suggested by the comment. For the second interpretation,
we don't need to give hints to implementors about not doing unnecessary work;
they already know they shouldn't do that. Either way, it should go.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4917"/>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[fs.op.weakly.canonical]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote><pre>
path filesystem::weakly_canonical(const path&amp; p);
path filesystem::weakly_canonical(const path&amp; p, error_code&amp; ec);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>-1- <i>Effects</i>: Using <tt>status(p)</tt> or <tt>status(p, ec)</tt>,
respectively, to determine existence, return a path composed by
<tt>operator/=</tt> from the result of calling <tt>canonical()</tt> with
a path argument composed of the leading elements of <tt>p</tt> that exist,
if any, followed by the elements of <tt>p</tt> that do not exist, if any.
For the first form, <tt>canonical()</tt> is called without an <tt>error_code</tt> argument.
For the second form, <tt>canonical()</tt> is called with <tt>ec</tt> as an
<tt>error_code</tt> argument, and <tt>path()</tt> is returned at the first
error occurrence, if any.
</p>
<p>-2- <i>Postconditions</i>: The returned path is in normal form
(<sref ref="[fs.path.generic]"/>).</p>
<p> -3- <i>Returns</i>: <tt>p</tt> with symlinks resolved and the result
normalized (<sref ref="[fs.path.generic]"/>).</p>
<p>-4- <i>Throws</i>: As specified in <sref ref="[fs.err.report]"/>.</p>
<p><del>-5- <i>Remarks</i>: Implementations should avoid unnecessary
normalization such as when <tt>canonical</tt> has already been called
on the entirety of <tt>p</tt>.</del>
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
