<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3441" status="New">
<title>Misleading note about calls to customization points</title>
<section><sref ref="[namespace.std]"/></section>
<submitter>Michael Park</submitter>
<date>08 May 2020</date>
<priority>1</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<a href="https://wg21.link/p0551">P0551</a> (Thou Shalt Not Specialize <tt>std</tt> Function Templates!) 
added a clause in [namespace.std]/7:
</p>
<blockquote style="border-left: 3px solid #ccc;padding-left: 15px;">
<p>
Other than in namespace <tt>std</tt> or in a namespace within namespace <tt>std</tt>, a program may provide 
an overload for any library function template designated as a customization point, provided that 
(a) the overload's declaration depends on at least one user-defined type and (b) the overload meets 
the standard library requirements for the customization point. (footnote 174) [<i>Note:</i> This permits a (qualified 
or unqualified) call to the customization point to invoke the most appropriate overload for 
the given arguments. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Given that <tt>std::swap</tt> is a designated customization point, the note seems to suggest the following:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
namespace N {
  struct X {};
  void swap(X&amp;, X&amp;) {}
}

N::X a, b;
std::swap(a, b); // <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bold">qualified call to customization point finds N::swap?</span>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
This is not what happens, as the call to <tt>std::swap</tt> does not find <tt>N::swap</tt>.
</p>

<note>2020-07-17; Priority set to 1 in telecon</note>
<p>Related to <iref ref="3442"/>.</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4861">N4861</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[namespace.std]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-7- Other than in namespace <tt>std</tt> or in a namespace within namespace <tt>std</tt>, a program 
may provide an overload for any library function template designated as a customization point, 
provided that (a) the overload's declaration depends on at least one user-defined type and (b) the 
overload meets the standard library requirements for the customization point. (footnote 173) 
<del>[<i>Note:</i> This permits a (qualified or unqualified) call to the customization point
to invoke the most appropriate overload for the given arguments. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]</del>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>
</issue>
