<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2986" status="New">
<title>Handling of multi-character collating elements by the <tt>regex</tt> FSM is underspecified</title>
<section><sref ref="[re.grammar]"/></section>
<submitter>Hubert Tong</submitter>
<date>25 Jun 2017</date>
<priority>4</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
In <a href="https://wg21.link/n4660">N4660</a> subclause 31.13 [re.grammar] paragraph 5:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The productions <tt>ClassAtomExClass</tt>, <tt>ClassAtomCollatingElement</tt> and <tt>ClassAtomEquivalence</tt> provide
functionality equivalent to that of the same features in regular expressions in POSIX.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The broadness of the above statement makes it sound like it is merely a statement of intent; however, this appears to 
be a necessary normative statement insofar as identifying the general semantics to be associated with the syntactic 
forms identified. In any case, if it is meant for <tt>ClassAtomCollatingElement</tt> to provide functionality equivalent 
to a collating symbol in a POSIX bracket expression, multi-character collating elements need to be considered.
<p/>
In [re.grammar] paragraph 14:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The behavior of the internal finite state machine representation when used to match a sequence of characters is 
as described in ECMA-262. The behavior is modified according to any <tt>match_flag_type</tt> flags specified when 
using the regular expression object in one of the regular expression algorithms. The behavior is also localized 
by interaction with the traits class template parameter as follows: [bullets 14.1 to 14.4]
</p></blockquote>
<p>
In none of the bullets does the wording handle multi-character collating elements in a clear manner:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>14.1 deals in characters.</p></li>
<li><p>14.2 deals in characters (<tt>traits_inst.translate</tt> accepts only a single character).</p></li>
<li><p>14.3 might handle a multi-character collating element; however, there is no specification of how 
such a collating element is to be identified from the sequence of characters. Additionally, the definition 
of primary equivalence class specifies that it is a set of characters (not of collating elements).</p></li>
<li><p>14.4 deals in characters.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>
The ECMA-262 specification for <em>ClassRanges</em> also deals in characters.
</p>

<note>2017-07 Toronto Monday issue prioritization</note>
<p>Priority 4</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>
</issue>
