<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4539" status="New">
<title>Undefined behavior in `std::bit_cast` should be diagnosed during constant evaluation</title>
<section>
<sref ref="[bit.cast]"/>
</section>
<submitter>Jan Schultke</submitter>
<date>10 Mar 2026</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
Consider the following example with undefined behavior, which assumes that `sizeof(int)` equals `4`:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
struct alignas(4) E { };
constexpr auto x = std::bit_cast&lt;int&gt;(E{});
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
The example compiles with MSVC without any error or warning, where `x` has the value `0`, 
which is valid if the UB is library UB; other compilers reject it.
<p/>
<sref ref="[bit.cast]"/> paragraph 4, bullet 2 explicitly states:
</p>
<blockquote style="border-left: 3px solid #ccc;padding-left: 15px;">
<p>
Otherwise, if <tt><i>b</i></tt> is indeterminate, the behavior is undefined.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
The fact that undefined behavior is called out explicitly within library wording suggests that this is 
"library UB", not "core UB" that would prevent the initializer from being a constant expression because 
it violates the requirement of <sref ref="[expr.const]"/> paragraph 21 bullet 2.3:
</p>
<blockquote style="border-left: 3px solid #ccc;padding-left: 15px;">
<p>
no constituent value of scalar type is an indeterminate or erroneous value (<sref ref="[basic.indet]"/>),
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Similarly, <sref ref="[bit.cast]"/> paragraph 4 states that forming a value representation that is not 
valid for the type is undefined, which may also be seen as "library UB".  This can occur in 
<tt>bit_cast&lt;bool&gt;(char{2})</tt> if `2` is not a valid representation of `bool`.
<p/>
During the 2026-03-10 LEWG telecon discussing <paper num="P3969R0"/>, LEWG polled whether this UB 
should be diagnosed.
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
POLL: The undefined behavior in `bit_cast` should be diagnosable during constexpr.<br/>
Attendance: 19<br/>
Authors' opinion: N/A<br/>
Outcome: No objection to unanimous consent.
</p>
</blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N5032"/>.
</p>

<ol>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[bit.cast]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
template&lt;class To, class From&gt;
  constexpr To bit_cast(const From&amp; from) noexcept;
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
-1- <i>Constraints</i>: [&hellip;]
<p/>
-2- <i>Mandates</i>: Neither `To` nor `From` are consteval-only types (<sref ref="[basic.types.general]"/>).
<p/>
-3- <i>Constant When</i>: `To`, `From`, and the types of all subobjects of `To` and `From` 
are types `T` such that: [&hellip;]
<p/>
-4- <i>Returns</i>: An object of type `To`. Implicitly creates objects nested within the result 
(<sref ref="[intro.object]"/>). Each bit of the value representation of the result is equal to the 
corresponding bit in the object representation of from. Padding bits of the result are unspecified. 
For the result and each object created within it, if there is no value of the object's type corresponding 
to the value representation produced, the behavior is undefined. If there are multiple such values, which 
value is produced is unspecified. A bit in the value representation of the result is indeterminate 
if it does not correspond to a bit in the value representation of from or corresponds to a bit for 
which the smallest enclosing object is not within its lifetime or has an indeterminate value 
(<sref ref="[basic.indet]"/>). A bit in the value representation of the result is erroneous if it 
corresponds to a bit for which the smallest enclosing object has an erroneous value. For each bit 
<tt><i>b</i></tt> in the value representation of the result that is indeterminate or erroneous, 
let <tt><i>u</i></tt> be the smallest object containing that bit enclosing <tt><i>b</i></tt>:
<p/>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
The result does not otherwise contain any indeterminate or erroneous values.
<p/>
<ins>-?- <i>Remarks</i>: A function call expression that has undefined or erroneous behavior as 
described above is not a core constant expression.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
