<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4043" status="New">
<title><code>"ASCII"</code> is not a registered character encoding</title>
<section><sref ref="[text.encoding.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Jonathan Wakely</submitter>
<date>23 Jan 2024</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The IANA Charater Sets registry does not contain "ASCII" as an alias of the
"US-ASCII" encoding. This is apparently for historical reasons, because there
used to be some ambiguity about exactly what "ASCII" meant. I don't think
those historical reasons are relevant to C++26, but the absence of "ASCII"
in the IANA registry means that it's not a registered character encoding
as defined by <sref ref="[text.encoding.general]"/>.
</p>

<p>
This means that the encoding referred to by notes in the C++ standard
(<sref ref="[fs.path.generic]"/>, <sref ref="[facet.numpunct.virtuals]"/>)
and by an example in the <code>std::text_encoding</code> proposal
(<paper num="P1885"/>) isn't actually usable in portable code.
So <code>std::text_encoding("ASCII")</code> creates an object with
<code>mib() == std::text_encoding::other</code>, which is not the same
encoding as <code>std::text_encoding("US-ASCII")</code>.
This seems surprising.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4971"/>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[text.encoding.general]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>-1-
A <i>registered character encoding</i> is a character encoding scheme
in the IANA Character Sets registry.
</p>
<p>
[<i>Note 1</i>:
The IANA Character Sets registry uses the term “character sets” to refer to character encodings.
&mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p>
<p>
The primary name of a registered character encoding is the name
of that encoding specified in the IANA Character Sets registry.
</p>

<p>-2-
The set of known registered character encodings contains every
registered character encoding specified in the IANA Character Sets registry
except for the following:
<ol style="list-style-type: none">
<li>(2.1) &ndash; NATS-DANO (33)</li>
<li>(2.2) &ndash; NATS-DANO-ADD (34)</li>
</ol>
</p>

<p>-3-
Each known registered character encoding is identified by an enumerator in
<code>text_encoding::id</code>, and has a set of zero or more <i>aliases</i>.
</p>

<p>-4-
The set of aliases of a known registered character encoding is an
implementation-defined superset of the aliases specified in the
IANA Character Sets registry.
<ins>The set of aliases for US-ASCII includes <code>"ASCII"</code>.</ins>
No two aliases or primary names of distinct registered character encodings
are equivalent when compared by <code>text_encoding::<i>comp-name</i></code>.
</p>

</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
