<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4149" status="New">
<title>User defined macros without standard headers (294 redux)</title>
<section><sref ref="[macro.names]"/></section>
<submitter>Jonathan Wakely</submitter>
<date>05 Sep 2024</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
Issue <iref ref="294"/> changed <sref ref="[macro.names]"/> from:
<blockquote>
A translation unit that includes a header shall not contain any macros that
define names declared or defined in that header. Nor shall such a translation
unit define macros for names lexically identical to keywords.
</blockquote>
to:
<blockquote>
A translation unit that includes a standard library header shall not
`#define` or `#undef` names declared in any standard library header.
<p>
A translation unit shall not `#define` or `#undef` names lexically identical
to keywords.
</p>
</blockquote>
</p>
<p>
Note that the second sentence of the original says "such a translation unit"
when prohibiting things like `#define while`. This means the prohibition only
applies to "a translation unit that includes a header".
The replacement has the prohibition in a separate paragraph and does not
clearly say that it only applies when a header is included.
</p>
<p>
The issue discussion seems clear that the concern is about C++ headers
including other unspecified headers, which is allowed in C++ (though not in C).
There is no justification for broadening the second sentence to apply
unconditionally. Such a rule would belong in <sref ref="[cpp]"/> anyway,
not in library wording. That overreach doesn't appear to have been intended,
and we should clarify what the library is prohibiting.
</p>
<p>
It was pointed out on the reflector that it's not enough to only prohibit
defining such macros <i>after</i> including headers, because in some cases
that could still break the library header. For example, the library macro
`assert` typically uses `void` and so `#define void ...` would break `assert`
even if it happens after including <code>&lt;cassert&gt;</code>.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4986"/>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[macro.names]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-1- A translation unit that includes a standard library header shall not
`#define` or `#undef` names declared in any standard library header.
</p>
<p>
-2- A translation unit
<ins>that includes a standard library header</ins>
shall not `#define` or `#undef` names lexically identical to keywords,
to the identifiers listed in Table 4,
or to the <i>attribute-tokens</i> described in <sref ref="[dcl.attr]"/>,
except that the names `likely` and `unlikely` may be defined as
function-like macros (<sref ref="[cpp.replace]"/>).
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
