<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2417" status="NAD">
<title>[fund.ts.v2] <tt>std::experimental::optional::operator&lt;</tt> and <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> requirement</title>
<section><sref ref="[optional.relops]"/> <sref ref="[optional.comp_with_t]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>20 Jun 2014</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses: fund.ts.v2</b></p>
<p>
Currently, <tt>std::experimental::optional::operator==</tt> imposes the <tt>EqualityComparable</tt> requirement which provides
two guarantees: It ensures that <tt>operator!=</tt> can rely on the equivalence-relation property and more importantly, that
the <tt>BooleanTestable</tt> requirements suggested by issue <iref ref="2114"/> are automatically implied.
<p/>
<tt>std::experimental::optional::operator&lt;</tt> doesn't provide a <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> requirement, but there was quite
an historic set of changes involved with that family of types: As of <a href="https://wg21.link/n3527.html">N3527</a>
this operator was defined in terms of <tt>operator&lt;</tt> of the contained type <tt>T</tt> and imposed the <tt>LessThanComparable</tt>
requirement. In the final acceptance step of <tt>optional</tt> by the committee, the definition was expressed in terms of <tt>std::less</tt>
and the <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> requirement had been removed.
<p/>
The inconsistency between <tt>operator==</tt> and <tt>operator&lt;</tt> should be removed. One possible course of action would be
to add the <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> to <tt>std::experimental::optional::operator&lt;</tt>. The <tt>EqualityComparable</tt> requirement
of <tt>operator==</tt> could also be removed, but in that case both operators would at least need to require the <tt>BooleanTestable</tt>
requirements (see <iref ref="2114"/>) for the result type of <tt>T</tt>'s <tt>operator==</tt> and <tt>operator&lt;</tt>.
<p/>
Arguably, corresponding operators for <tt>pair</tt> and <tt>tuple</tt> do not impose <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> (nor
<tt>EqualityComparable</tt>), albeit the definition of the "derived" relation functions depend on properties ensured by
<tt>LessThanComparable</tt>. According to the <a href="https://www.sgi.com/tech/stl/pair.html">SGI definition</a>, the intention was
to imposed both <tt>EqualityComparable</tt> and <tt>LessThanComparable</tt>. If this is not intended, the standard should clarify
this position.
</p>

<note>2015-02 Cologne</note>
<p>
VV, DK, JY discuss why and when <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> was removed. AM: Move to LEWG. Please tell LWG when you look at it.
</p>

<note>2016-11-08, Issaquah</note>
<p>Not adopted during NB comment resolution</p>

<note>LEWG Kona 2017</note>
<p>Recommend NAD: We've done a lot of work getting the C++17 semantics we want in this area; we're not going to change
them 3 days from DIS or change the TSv2 behavior to be different from '17.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
