<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4136" status="New">
<title>Specify behavior of [linalg] Hermitian algorithms on diagonal with nonzero imaginary part</title>
<section><sref ref="[linalg.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Mark Hoemmen</submitter>
<date>09 Aug 2024</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
Mathematically, the diagonal elements of a Hermitian matrix must all
have zero imaginary part (if they are complex numbers). <sref ref="[linalg.general]"/> 
paragraphs 3 and 4 govern the behavior of [linalg]
functions that operate on "symmetric," "Hermitian," or "triangular"
matrices. All such functions only access the specified triangle
(lower or upper) of the matrix. Whatever is in the other triangle of
the matrix doesn't matter; it's not even accessed. That gives
well-defined behavior for "symmetric" and "triangular" matrices.
However, both triangles include the diagonal. What should the
"Hermitian" functions do if they encounter a diagonal element with
nonzero imaginary part?
<p/>
The current wording says that both the operation performed and the
matrix itself are Hermitian, but does not clarify what happens if the
latter is not true. For example, <sref ref="[linalg.algs.blas2.hemv]"/> 
says that <tt>hermitian_matrix_vector_product</tt> performs a 
</p>
<blockquote style="border-left: 3px solid #ccc;padding-left: 15px;">
<p>
Hermitian matrix-vector product, taking into account the <tt>Triangle</tt> 
parameter that applies to the Hermitian matrix <tt>A</tt> (<sref ref="[linalg.general]"/>).
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Language like this appears in the specifications of all the functions 
whose names start with <tt>hermitian</tt>. The implication is that if 
the diagonal has an element with nonzero imaginary part, then the matrix 
is not Hermitian and therefore a precondition of the function has been violated.  
The result is undefined behavior.
<p/>
We can get rid of this undefined behavior by defining what happens in
this case. It turns out that Chapter 2 of the BLAS Standard already
does this: It says that the Hermitian algorithms do not access the
imaginary parts of diagonal elements. The reference Fortran BLAS
implementations of <tt>CHEMV</tt> (single-precision Complex HErmitian
Matrix-Vector product) and <tt>ZHEMV</tt> (double-precision complex 
HErmitian Matrix-Vector product) follow the BLAS Standard. <tt>CHEMV</tt> 
uses <tt>real(A(j,j))</tt> and <tt>ZHEMV</tt> uses <tt>dble(A(j,j))</tt>, 
which means that the BLAS routines only access the real part of each diagonal 
element.
<p/>
The clear design intent of <paper num="P1673R13"/> was to imitate the 
behavior of the BLAS Standard and reference BLAS unless otherwise specified.  
Thus, we propose to specify this behavior in the wording; we do not think 
this requires LEWG re-review.
<p/>
In my view, it's fine to retain the existing wording like that in
<sref ref="[linalg.algs.blas2.hemv]"/>, that refers to a "Hermitian matrix".  
The matrix defined by the revised [linalg.general] instructions is
unambiguously a Hermitian matrix. Just like the "other triangle" of a
symmetric or triangular matrix does not affect the behavior of
[linalg] symmetric resp. triangular algorithms, the wording fix here
will ensure that any imaginary parts of diagonal elements will not
affect the behavior of [linalg] Hermitian algorithms.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4988"/>.
</p>

<ol>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[linalg.general]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-4- For any function <tt>F</tt> that takes a parameter named <tt>t</tt>, <tt>t</tt> 
applies to accesses done through the parameter preceding <tt>t</tt> in the parameter 
list of <tt>F</tt>. Let <tt>m</tt> be such an access-modified function parameter. 
<tt>F</tt> will only access the triangle of <tt>m</tt> specified by <tt>t</tt>. 
<ins>For accesses of diagonal elements <tt>m[i, i]</tt>, <tt>F</tt> will use the value
<tt><i>real-if-needed</i>(m[i, i])</tt> if the name of <tt>F</tt> starts with 
<tt>hermitian</tt>.</ins>
For accesses <tt>m[i, j]</tt> outside the triangle specified by <tt>t</tt>, <tt>F</tt> 
will use the value [&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
