<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2184" status="New">
<title>Muddled allocator requirements for <tt>match_results</tt> assignments</title>
<section><sref ref="[re.results.const]"/> <sref ref="[re.results.all]"/></section>
<submitter>Pete Becker</submitter>
<date>29 Aug 2012</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>

<p>
The effects of the two assignment operators are specified in Table 141. Table 141 makes no mention of allocators, 
so, presumably, they don't touch the target object's allocator. That's okay, but it leaves the question: 
<tt>match_results::get_allocator()</tt> is supposed to return "A copy of the Allocator that was passed to the 
object's constructor or, if that allocator has been replaced, a copy of the most recent replacement"; if assignment 
doesn't replace the allocator, how can the allocator be replaced?
</p>

<note>2018-06-04, Daniel comments and provides wording</note>
<p>
Similar to the reasoning provided in the 2018-06-02 comment in LWG <iref ref="2183"/>, it is possible to refer to 
the introductory wording of <tt>match_results</tt> which says in <sref ref="[re.results]"/> p2:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The class template <tt>match_results</tt> satisfies the requirements of an allocator-aware container and 
of a sequence container (26.2.1, 26.2.3) except that only operations defined for const-qualified sequence 
containers are supported and that the semantics of comparison functions are different from those required 
for a container.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Again, similar to LWG <iref ref="2183"/>, this allows us to deduce the required effects of the copy/move
assignment operators discussed here, because <sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/> p8 also says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[&hellip;] The allocator may be replaced only via assignment or <tt>swap()</tt>. Allocator replacement is 
performed by copy assignment, move assignment, or swapping of the allocator only if 
<tt>allocator_traits&lt;allocator_type&gt;::propagate_on_container_copy_assignment::value</tt>,
<tt>allocator_traits&lt;allocator_type&gt;::propagate_on_container_move_assignment::value</tt>, or 
<tt>allocator_traits&lt;allocator_type&gt;::propagate_on_container_swap::value</tt> is <tt>true</tt> 
within the implementation of the corresponding container operation. In all container types defined in 
this Clause, the member <tt>get_allocator()</tt> returns a copy of the allocator used to construct the 
container or, if that allocator has been replaced, a copy of the most recent replacement. [&hellip;]
</p></blockquote>
<p>
So this wording already specifies everything we need, <em>except</em> for the problem that
<sref ref="[re.results]"/> p2 quoted above restricts to operations supported by a const-qualified sequence 
container, which of-course would exclude the copy assignment and the move assignment operators.
But given that these mutable definitions are defined for <tt>match_results</tt>, it seems that the only fix 
needed is to adjust <sref ref="[re.results]"/> p2 a bit to ensure that both assignment operators are 
covered (again) by the general allocator-aware container wording. 
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="http://wg21.link/n4750">N4750</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Edit <sref ref="[re.results]"/> as indicated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
-2- The class template <tt>match_results</tt> satisfies the requirements of an allocator-aware container 
and of a sequence container (<sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/>, <sref ref="[sequence.reqmts]"/>) 
except that <ins>besides copy assignment and move assignment</ins> only operations defined for 
const-qualified sequence containers are supported and that the semantics of comparison functions are 
different from those required for a container.
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
