<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3259" status="WP">
<title>The definition of <i>constexpr iterators</i> should be adjusted</title>
<section><sref ref="[iterator.requirements.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>18 Aug 2019</date>
<priority>0</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The current definition of <i>constexpr iterators</i> is specified in 
<sref ref="[iterator.requirements.general]"/> p16 as follows:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
Iterators are called <i>constexpr iterators</i> if all operations provided to 
meet iterator category requirements are constexpr functions, except for
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: none">
<li><p>(16.1) &mdash; a pseudo-destructor call (<sref ref="[expr.prim.id.dtor]"/>), and</p></li>
<li><p>(16.2) &mdash; the construction of an iterator with a singular value.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>
With the acceptance of some proposals during the Cologne 2019 meeting, these additional 
requirements become mostly obsolete, as it had already been pointed out during that meeting:
<p/>
With the acceptance of <a href="https://wg21.link/p0784r7">P0784R7</a>, destructors can be 
declared <tt>constexpr</tt> and it is possible to perform a pseudo-destructor call within a 
constant expression, so bullet (16.1) is no longer a necessary requirement.
<p/>
With the acceptance of <a href="https://wg21.link/p1331r2">P1331R2</a>, trivial default 
initialization in constexpr contexts is now possible, and there is no longer a requirement
to initialize all sub-objects of a class object within a constant expression.
<p/>
It seems to me that we should simply strike the above two constraining requirements of the
definition of <i>constexpr iterators</i> for C++20.
</p>

<note>2019-09-14 Issue Prioritization</note>
<p>Status to Tentatively Ready and priority to 0 after five positive votes on the reflector.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4830">N4830</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[iterator.requirements.general]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-16- Iterators are called <i>constexpr iterators</i> if all operations provided to 
meet iterator category requirements are constexpr functions<ins>.</ins><del>, except for</del>
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: none">
<li><p><del>(16.1) &mdash; a pseudo-destructor call (<sref ref="[expr.prim.id.dtor]"/>), and</del></p></li>
<li><p><del>(16.2) &mdash; the construction of an iterator with a singular value.</del></p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>
</issue>
