<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3251" status="New">
<title>Are <tt>std::format</tt> alignment specifiers applied to string arguments?</title>
<section><sref ref="[format.string]"/></section>
<submitter>Richard Smith</submitter>
<date>2 Aug 2019</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
We are told:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
Formatting of objects of arithmetic types and <tt>const void*</tt> is done as if by 
calling <tt>to_chars</tt> (unless otherwise specified) and copying the output through 
the output iterator of the format context with additional padding and adjustments 
as specified by the format specifiers.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
&hellip; but there is no corresponding rule for strings. Is an alignment specifier 
intended to be applied to strings or not? The wording as-is is ambiguous.
<p/>
(The above also doesn't cover formatting <tt>void*</tt> or <tt>std::nullptr_t</tt>. 
Presumably at least those two should have the relevant adjustments applied to them!)
<p/>
The wording never actually anywhere says that the <tt>basic_format_args</tt> are in 
any way involved in the formatting process, or how formatting actually happens. 
(The wording doesn't say that <tt>basic_format_arg::handle::format</tt> is ever 
called, for example.)
<p/>
<b>Victor Zverovich:</b>
<p/>
An alignment specifier is intended to be applied to strings as well, <tt>void*</tt> and 
<tt>std::nullptr_t</tt> are converted into <tt>const void*</tt> when constructing 
<tt>basic_format_arg</tt>.
<p/>
The wording for <tt>vformat</tt> and similar functions says that <tt>basic_format_args</tt> is involved:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
<i>Returns:</i> A string object holding the character representation of formatting arguments
 provided by <tt>args</tt> formatted according to specifications given in <tt>fmt</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
but I admit that it is hand-wavy. Perhaps we could add something along the lines of
</p>
<blockquote><p>
For each replacement field referring to the argument with index <tt>(arg-id) i</tt>, the 
<tt>basic_format_arg</tt> object referring to the argument is obtained via <tt>args.get(i)</tt> 
and the <tt>parse</tt> and <tt>format</tt> functions of the <tt>formatter</tt> specialization 
for the underlying argument type are called to parse the format specification and format the value.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
to clarify how we format <tt>args</tt> (<tt>basic_format_args</tt>).
</p>

<note>2019-08-21 Priority set to 2 based on reflector discussion</note>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>
</issue>
