<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4019" status="SG9">
<title>Reversing an infinite range leads to an infinite loop</title>
<section><sref ref="[range.reverse]"/></section>
<submitter>Barry Revzin</submitter>
<date>25 Nov 2023</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
Consider the following:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
auto a = views::iota(0) | views::reverse;
auto b = views::repeat(42) | views::reverse;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
Here, <tt>views::iota(0)</tt> and <tt>views::repeat(42)</tt> are both non-common bidirectional (even random-access) ranges. 
They are also infinite ranges, even if the standard doesn't really recognize that. 
<p/>
<tt>views::reverse</tt> on a non-common range will actually compute the end iterator for you. So while both declarations 
of <tt>a</tt> and <tt>b</tt> above compile, attempting to use either in any way will lead to an infinite loop when you 
<tt>try a.begin()</tt> or <tt>b.begin()</tt>.
<p/>
A reddit post suggested disallowing reversing a non-common range but that likely breaks reasonable use-cases. We could at
the very least recognize ranges whose sentinel is <tt>unreachable_t</tt> and reject those from consideration. For instance, 
we could change <sref ref="[range.iter.op.next]"/>/3 to <i>Mandate</i> that <tt>S</tt> is not <tt>unreachable_t</tt>.
</p>

<note>2024-03-11; Reflector poll</note>
<p>
Set priority to 3 after reflector poll. Ask SG9 to look. Probably needs a paper.
</p>
<p>
Infinite ranges are invalid and giving an invalid range to the library is
undefined. But this is not a particularly satisfactory answer given that
we provide such ranges ourselves...
</p>

<note>St. Louis 2024-06-28; LWG and SG9 joint session</note>
<p>
Poll: SG9 and LWG believe this is not a defect?
<pre>
|SF| F| N| A|SA|
| 3| 3| 0| 2| 0|
</pre>
Weak consensus => needs to go to LEWG
</p>
<p>
Poll: SG9 and LWG agree that standard could do something to create
fewer sharp edges here, and we encourage a paper exploring options.
<pre>
|SF| F| N| A|SA|
| 4| 2| 2| 0| 0|
</pre>
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
