<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3419" status="Tentatively Ready">
<title>&sect;[algorithms.requirements]/15 doesn't reserve as many rights as it intends to</title>
<section><sref ref="[algorithms.requirements]"/></section>
<submitter>Richard Smith</submitter>
<date>24 Mar 2020</date>
<priority>0</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<sref ref="[algorithms.requirements]"/>/15 says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"The number and order of deducible template parameters for algorithm declarations are unspecified, except 
where explicitly stated otherwise. [<i>Note:</i> Consequently, the algorithms may not be called with 
explicitly-specified template argument lists. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]"
</p></blockquote>
<p>
But the note doesn't follow from the normative rule. For example, we felt the need to explicitly allow 
deduction for <tt>min</tt>'s template parameter:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;typename T&gt; const T&amp; min(const T&amp;, const T&amp;);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
&hellip; but if only the order and number of <em>deducible</em> template parameters is permitted to vary, 
then because of the required deduction behavior of this function template, there are only three possible 
valid declarations:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;typename T&gt; ??? min(const T&amp;, const T&amp;);
template&lt;typename T, typename U&gt; ??? min(const T&amp;, const U&amp;);
template&lt;typename T, typename U&gt; ??? min(const U&amp;, const T&amp;);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
(up to minor differences in the parameter type). This doesn't prohibit calls with an explicitly-specified 
template argument list, contrary to the claim in the note. (Indeed, because a call such as <tt>min(1, {})</tt> 
is valid, either the first of the above three overloads must be present or there must be a default template 
argument <tt>typename U = T</tt>, which further adds to the fact that there may be valid calls with an 
explicitly-specified template argument list.)
<p/>
Also, the "explicitly stated otherwise" cases use phrasing such as: "An invocation may explicitly specify 
an argument for the template parameter <tt>T</tt> of the overloads in namespace <tt>std</tt>." which 
doesn't "specify otherwise" the normative rule, but does "specify otherwise" the claim in the note.
<p/>
All this leads me to believe that [algorithms.requirements]/15 is backwards: the normative rule should be a 
note and the note should be the normative rule.
</p>

<note>2020-04-04 Issue Prioritization</note> 
<p>
Status set to Tentatively Ready after six positive votes on the reflector.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <a href="http://wg21.link/n4861">N4861</a>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[algorithms.requirements]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-15- The <ins>well-formedness and behavior of a call to an algorithm with an explicitly-specified template 
argument list is</ins><del>number and order of deducible template parameters for algorithm declarations are</del> 
unspecified, except where explicitly stated otherwise. [<i>Note:</i> Consequently, <ins>an implementation can 
declare an algorithm with different template parameters than those presented</ins><del>the algorithms may not be 
called with explicitly-specified template argument lists</del>. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>
</issue>
