<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4356" status="Open">
<title>`connect()` should use `get_allocator(get_env(rcvr))` to allocate the coroutine-state for a 
<tt><i>connect-awaitable</i></tt> coroutine</title>
<section>
<sref ref="[exec.connect]"/>
</section>
<submitter>Lewis Baker</submitter>
<date>27 Aug 2025</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The wording for `connect()` (<sref ref="[exec.connect]"/>) handles passing awaitable types as the sender argument 
by calling the <tt><i>connect-awaitable</i></tt>() coroutine and having it execute a `co_await` expression.
<p/>
The <tt><i>connect-awaitable</i></tt>() coroutine will typically need to dynamically allocate storage for 
the coroutine state and, as specified, this currently just always uses the global default allocator.
This is because the <tt><i>connect-awaitable-promise</i></tt> type does not define any member operator 
`new/delete` overloads.
<p/>
It seems desirable for this facility to use the allocator obtained from the receiver, by calling 
`get_allocator(get_env(rcvr))`, in order to allocate storage for the coroutine-state instead of always 
using global operator `new`. This would give the user at least some level of control over how this 
allocation is performed.
</p>

<note>2025-10-23; Reflector poll.</note>
<p>
Set priority to 2 after reflector poll.
</p>
<p>
"The `get_allocator` query doesn't have a default and I think that isn't
covered in the proposed resolution."
</p>
<note>2026-05-15; LWG telecon. Status: New &rarr; Open.</note>
<p>
SG1 discussed this in November and responded:
<blockquote>
Poll: SG1 recommends to specify that the destruction and the deallocation
of coroutine state happens before emitting senders/receivers completion signal
for LWG4356. Outcome: Strong consensus in favor.
</blockquote>
</p>
<p>
LWG discussion decided that the wording needs to say something like
"using the allocator obtained from `get_allocator(get_env(rcvr))` if that
expression is well-formed, and from <code>allocator&lt;byte&gt;()</code>
otherwise." The ordering problem identified by SG1 wouldn't be a problem if
it always used `std::allocator`, but obtaining an allocator from the
environment introduces the potential lifetime issue. Since everything in
<sref ref="[exec.connect]"/> is specified in code, that code should be updated
to include obtaining and using an allocator for the coroutine frame,
and destroying and deallocating everything before the completion signal.
This needs a lot of work.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N5014"/>.
</p>

<ol>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[exec.connect]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote class="note">
<p>
[<i>Drafting note: </i> This should cover the design intent, although we may want to spell this out 
more explicitly in terms of the exact semantics in a similar way to <sref ref="[coro.generator.promise]"/> p17, 
which lists overloads of operator `new()` and describes the rebound allocator type which allocates storage 
in chunks of size `__STDCPP_DEFAULT_NEW_ALIGNMENT__`.]
</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
<p>
-5- Let `V` name the type <tt><i>await-result-type</i>&lt;DS, <i>connect-awaitable-promise</i>&gt;</tt>, 
let `Sigs` name the type
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
[&hellip;]
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
and let <tt><i>connect-awaitable</i></tt> be an exposition-only coroutine defined as follows:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
namespace std::execution {
  [&hellip;]
}  
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
<ins>Any dynamically allocated storage required for the coroutine state allocated by an invocation 
of the form <tt><i>connect-awaitable</i>(sndr, rcvr)</tt> is allocated using the allocator obtained 
from `get_allocator(get_env(rcvr))`.</ins>
<p/>
-6- [&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>

</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
