<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3229" status="New">
<title>&sect;[res.on.exception.handling]#3 cannot apply to types with implicitly declared destructors</title>
<section><sref ref="[res.on.exception.handling]"/></section>
<submitter>Nevin Liber</submitter>
<date>28 Jun 2019</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<sref ref="[res.on.exception.handling]"/>#3 says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
Destructor operations defined in the C++ standard library shall not throw exceptions. 
Every destructor in the C++ standard library shall behave as if it had a non-throwing 
exception specification.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
However, types like <tt>pair</tt> and <tt>array</tt> have implicitly declared destructors, 
where <sref ref="[except.spec]"/>#8 applies:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The exception specification for an implicitly-declared destructor, or a destructor without 
a <i>noexcept</i>-specifier, is potentially-throwing if and only if any of the destructors 
for any of its potentially constructed subobjects is potentially-throwing or the destructor 
is virtual and the destructor of any virtual base class is potentially throwing.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
We can relax <sref ref="[res.on.exception.handling]"/> to only cover explicitly declared 
destructors because if they hold a user type where the destructor throws then we get UB 
from <sref ref="[res.on.functions]"/>#2: 
</p>
<blockquote><p>
In particular, the effects are undefined in the following cases: [&hellip;] 
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type:none">
<li><p>[&hellip;]</p></li>
<li><p>(2.4) &mdash; if any replacement function or handler function or destructor operation 
exits via an exception, unless specifically allowed in the applicable 
<i>Required behavior:</i> paragraph.</p></li>
<li><p>[&hellip;]</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>
and the referred to UB happens before [res.on.exception.handling] could apply.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="http://wg21.link/n4820">N4820</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[res.on.exception.handling]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote><p>
-3- Destructor operations defined in the C++ standard library shall not throw exceptions. 
Every <ins>explicitly declared</ins> destructor in the C++ standard library shall behave 
as if it had a non-throwing exception specification.
</p></blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>
</issue>
