<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2234" status="Open">
<title><tt>assert()</tt> should allow usage in constant expressions</title>
<section><sref ref="[assertions]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>12 Jan 2013</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
It is unclear from the current specification whether <tt>assert()</tt> expressions can be used in 
(potential) constant expressions. As an example consider the implementation of a <tt>constexpr</tt>
function:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;cassert&gt;

template&lt;class T, unsigned N&gt;
struct array {
  T data[N];
  constexpr const T&amp; operator[](unsigned i) const {
    return assert(i &lt; N), data[i];
  }
};

int main() {
  constexpr array&lt;int, 3&gt; ai = {1, 2, 3};
  constexpr int i = ai[0];
  int j = ai[0];
  // constexpr int k = ai[5];
}
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
The first question is whether this program is guaranteed well-formed? A second question is whether is would guaranteed to be
ill-formed, if we uncomment the last code line in <tt>main()</tt>?
</p>

<p>
The wording in <sref ref="[assertions]"/> doesn't add anything significant to the C99 wording. From the C99 specification 
(7.2 p1 and 7.2.1.1 p2) we get already some valuable guarantees:
</p>

<ul>
<li><p>
The expression <tt>assert(e)</tt> is a <tt>void</tt> expression for all expressions <tt>e</tt> independent of 
the definition of <tt>NDEBUG</tt>.
</p></li>
<li><p>
If <tt>NDEBUG</tt> is defined, <tt>assert(e)</tt> is equivalent to the expression <tt>void()</tt>
(or anything that cannot be distinguished from that).
</p></li>
</ul>

<p>
The current wording does not yet <em>guarantee</em> that <tt>assert</tt> expressions can be used in constant expressions,
but all tested implementations (gcc, MSVC) would already support this use-case. It seems to me that this should be possible
without giving <tt>assert</tt> a special meaning for the core language.
<p/>
As a related comment it should be added, that there is a core language 
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2012/n3444.html">proposal</a> 
that intents to relax some current constraints for <tt>constexpr</tt> functions and <tt>literal</tt> types. The most 
interesting one (making <tt>void</tt> a literal types and allowing for expression-statements) would simplify the motivating 
example implementation of <tt>operator[]</tt> to:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
constexpr const T&amp; operator[](unsigned i) const {
  assert(i &lt; N);
  return data[i];
};
</pre></blockquote>

<note>2013-03-15 Issues Teleconference</note>
<p>
Moved to Open.
</p>
<p>
We are still gaining experience with <tt>constexpr</tt> as a language feature, and there may
be work in Evolution that would help address some of these concerns.  Defer discussion until
we have a group familiar with any evolutionary direction.
</p>

<note>2014-06-08, Daniel comments and suggests wording</note>
<p>
After approval of <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2013/n3652.html"/>N3652<a/>,
<tt>void</tt> is now a literal type and <tt>constexpr</tt> functions can contain multiple statements, so
this makes the guarantee that <tt>assert</tt> expressions are per-se  <tt>constexpr</tt>-friendly even more
relevant. A possible wording form could be along the lines of:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
For every core constant expression <em>e</em> of scalar type that evaluates to <tt>true</tt> after being contextually 
converted to <tt>bool</tt>, the expression <tt>assert(<em>e</em>)</tt> shall be a prvalue core constant expression of type 
<tt>void</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Richard Smith pointed out some weaknesses of this wording form, for example it would not guarantee to require
the following example to work:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
constexpr void check(bool b) { assert(b); }
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
because <tt>b</tt> is not a core constant expression in this context.
<p/>
He suggested improvements that lead to the wording form presented below (any defects mine). 
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3936.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Introduce the following new definition to the existing list in <sref ref="[definitions]"/>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
<strong>constant subexpression</strong> [defns.const.subexpr]
<p/>
an expression whose evaluation as subexpression of a <em>conditional-expression</em> <em>CE</em> (<sref ref="[expr.cond]"/>) 
would not prevent <em>CE</em> from being a core constant expression (<sref ref="[expr.cond]"/>).
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Insert a new paragraph following <sref ref="[assertions]"/> p1 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
<ins>-?- Given an expression <tt><em>e</em></tt>, if either</ins>
</p>
<ul>
<li><p><ins><tt>NDEBUG</tt> is defined at the point where <tt>assert(<em>e</em>)</tt> is evaluated, or</ins></p></li>
<li><p><ins><tt><em>e</em></tt> contextually converted to <tt>bool</tt>, is a constant subexpression (<sref ref="[defns.const.subexpr]"/>), 
that evaluates to <tt>true</tt>,</ins></p></li>
</ul>
<p>
<ins>the expression <tt>assert(<em>e</em>)</tt> is a constant subexpression.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
