<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2398" status="New">
<title><tt>type_info</tt>'s destructor shouldn't be required to be virtual</title>
<section><sref ref="[type.info]"/></section>
<submitter>Stephan T. Lavavej</submitter>
<date>14 Jun 2014</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<tt>type_info</tt>'s destructor is depicted as being <tt>virtual</tt>, which is nearly unobservable to users (since they can't construct 
or copy this class, they can't usefully derive from it). However, it's technically observable (via <tt>is_polymorphic</tt> and 
<tt>has_virtual_destructor</tt>). It also imposes real costs on implementations, requiring them to store one vptr per 
<tt>type_info</tt> object, when RTTI space consumption is a significant concern.
<p/>
Making this implementation-defined wouldn't affect users (who can observe this only if they're specifically looking for it) and 
wouldn't affect implementations who need <tt>virtual</tt> here, but it would allow other implementations to drop <tt>virtual</tt> 
and improve their RTTI space consumption.
<p/>
Richard Smith:
<p/>
It's observable in a few other ways.
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
std::map&lt;void*, something&gt; m;
m[dynamic_cast&lt;void*&gt;(&amp;typeid(blah))] = stuff;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
... is broken by this change, because you can't <tt>dynamic_cast</tt> a non-polymorphic class type to <tt>void*</tt>.
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
type_info&amp; f();
typeid(f());
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
... evaluates <tt>f()</tt> at runtime without this change, and might not do so with this change.
<p/>
These are probably rare things, but I can imagine at least some forms of the latter being used in SFINAE tricks.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3936.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Change <sref ref="[type.info]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
namespace std {
  class type_info {
  public:
    <del>virtual</del><ins><i>see below</i></ins> ~type_info();
    [&hellip;]
  };
}
</pre>
<p>
-1- The class <tt>type_info</tt> describes type information generated by the implementation. Objects of this class
effectively store a pointer to a name for the type, and an encoded value suitable for comparing two types for
equality or collating order. The names, encoding rule, and collating sequence for types are all unspecified
and may differ between programs. <ins>Whether <tt>~type_info()</tt> is <tt>virtual</tt> is implementation-defined.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
