<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4042" status="New">
<title><tt>std::print</tt> should permit an efficient implementation</title>
<section><sref ref="[print.fun]"/></section>
<submitter>Victor Zverovich</submitter>
<date>20 Jan 2024</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<tt>std::print</tt>/<tt>std::vprint*</tt> is currently defined in terms of formatting into a temporary string, e.g. 
<sref ref="[print.fun]"/>:
</p>
<blockquote>
<pre>
void vprint_nonunicode(FILE* stream, string_view fmt, format_args args);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Preconditions</i>: <tt>stream</tt> is a valid pointer to an output C stream.
<p/>
<i>Effects</i>: Writes the result of <tt>vformat(fmt, args)</tt> to <tt>stream</tt>.
<p/>
<i>Throws</i>: Any exception thrown by the call to <tt>vformat</tt> (<sref ref="[format.err.report]"/>).
 <tt>system_error</tt> if writing to <tt>stream</tt> fails. May throw <tt>bad_alloc</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>
This is done to make it clear that noninterleaved output is desired while keeping specification simple and portable.
<p/>
Unfortunately, the current specification seems to prohibit a more efficient implementation that performs formatting 
directly into a stream buffer under a lock (<tt>flockfile</tt>/<tt>funlockfile</tt> in POSIX) like <tt>printf</tt> does. 
The difference can be observable in case of an I/O error that occurs before a custom formatter is called. In the 
(double buffered) implementation that directly follows the spec all formatters will be called, while in a more efficient 
(locking) implementation subsequent formatters may not be called.
<p/>
The easiest fix, given in the current proposed resolution, is to say that some arguments may not be formatted in 
case of a write error. It might be a bit weird considering that the spec says that we construct a string first so an 
alternative resolution is to replace <tt>vformat</tt> with <tt>vformat_to</tt> info some unspecified buffer iterator 
and state noninterleaving requirement separately. 
</p>

<note>2024-02-19; Feb 2024 mailing</note>
<p>This would be resolved by <paper num="P3107"/>.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4971"/>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[print.fun]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
void vprint_unicode(FILE* stream, string_view fmt, format_args args);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
-6- <i>Preconditions</i>: <tt>stream</tt> is a valid pointer to an output C stream.
<p/>
-7- <i>Effects</i>: The function initializes an automatic variable via
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
string out = vformat(fmt, args);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
If <tt>stream</tt> refers to a terminal capable of displaying Unicode, writes out to the terminal using the
native Unicode API; if out contains invalid code units, the behavior is undefined and implementations
are encouraged to diagnose it. Otherwise writes <tt>out</tt> to <tt>stream</tt> unchanged. If the native 
Unicode API is used, the function flushes <tt>stream</tt> before writing <tt>out</tt>.
<p/>
<ins>If writing to the terminal or <tt>stream</tt> fails, some arguments in <tt>args</tt> may not be formatted.</ins>
<p/>
[&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
[&hellip;]
<pre>
void vprint_nonunicode(FILE* stream, string_view fmt, format_args args);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
-11- <i>Preconditions</i>: <tt>stream</tt> is a valid pointer to an output C stream.
<p/>
-12- <i>Effects</i>: Writes the result of <tt>vformat(fmt, args)</tt> to <tt>stream</tt>. <ins>If writing to 
<tt>stream</tt> fails, some arguments in <tt>args</tt> may not be formatted.</ins>
<p/>
-13- <i>Throws</i>: [&hellip;].
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
