<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="4087" status="New">
<title>Standard exception messages have unspecified encoding</title>
<section><sref ref="[exception]"/></section>
<submitter>Victor Zverovich</submitter>
<date>28 Apr 2024</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The null-terminated multibyte string returned by the <tt>what</tt> method of <tt>std::exception</tt> 
and its subclasses in the standard has an unspecified encoding. The closest thing in the specification 
is the "suitable for conversion and display as a <tt>wstring</tt>" part in <i>Remarks</i> 
(<sref ref="[exception]"/> p6) but it is too vague to be useful because anything can be converted to 
<tt>wstring</tt> in one way or another:
</p>
<blockquote>
<pre>
virtual const char* what() const noexcept;
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Returns</i>: An implementation-defined <span style="font-variant:small-caps">ntbs</span>.
<p/>
<i>Remarks</i>: The message may be a null-terminated multibyte string (<sref ref="[multibyte.strings]"/>), 
suitable for conversion and display as a <tt>wstring</tt> (<sref ref="[string.classes]"/>, 
<sref ref="[locale.codecvt]"/>). The return value remains valid until the exception object from which it 
is obtained is destroyed or a non-<tt>const</tt> member function of the exception object is called.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>
As a result, it is impossible to portably use the exception message, e.g. print it. Since exception 
messages are commonly combined with string literals and are often constructed from string literals, 
at the very least the standard should say that the message is compatible with them, i.e. that it is 
in the ordinary literal encoding or its subset.
<p/>
To give a specific example of this problem, consider the following code compiled on Windows with 
Microsoft Visual C++, the ordinary literal encoding of UTF-8 and the system locale set to Belarusian 
(the language of the text in this example):
</p>
<blockquote>
<pre>
std::uintmax_t size = 0;
try {
  size = std::filesystem::file_size(L"Шчучыншчына");
} catch (const std::exception&amp; e) {
  std::print("Памылка: {}", e.what());
}
</pre>
</blockquote>
<p>
Since both <tt>std::filesystem::path</tt> and <tt>std::print</tt> support Unicode one would expect this 
to work and, when run, print a readable error message if the file "Шчучыншчына" doesn't exist. However, 
the output will be corrupted instead. The reason for the corruption is that <tt>filesystem_error</tt> 
requires including the path in the message but doesn't say that it should be transcoded 
(<sref ref="[fs.filesystem.error.members]"/> p7):
</p>
<blockquote>
<pre>
virtual const char* what() const noexcept;
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Returns</i>: An <span style="font-variant:small-caps">ntbs</span> that incorporates the <tt>what_arg</tt> 
argument supplied to the constructor. The exact format is unspecified. Implementations should include the 
<tt>system_error::what()</tt> string and the pathnames of <tt>path1</tt> and <tt>path2</tt> in the native 
format in the returned string.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>
Therefore, the message will contain literal text in the ordinary literal encoding (UTF-8) combined with a 
path, most likely in the operating system dependent current encoding for pathnames which in this case is CP1251. 
So different parts of the output will be in two incompatible encodings and therefore unusable with 
<tt>std::print</tt> or any other facility.
<p/>
The actual observable behavior for the above example is no output in the Windows console which 
is extremely broken but appears to be conformant with the current specification. It was reproduced with 
{fmt}'s implementation of <tt>print</tt> since Microsoft STL doesn't implement <tt>std::print</tt> yet. 
Replacing <tt>std::print</tt> with another output facility produces a different but equally unusable form 
of mojibake.
</p>

<note>2024-05-04; Daniel comments</note>
<p>
The proposed wording is incomplete. There are about 12 other <tt>what</tt> specifications in the Standard
Library with exactly the same specification as <tt>exception::what</tt> that would either need to get the 
same treatment or we would need general wording somewhere that says that the specification "contract" of 
<tt>exception::what</tt> extends to all of its derived classes. A third choice could be that we introduce 
a new definition such as an <span style="font-variant:small-caps">lntbs</span> (or maybe "literal 
<span style="font-variant:small-caps">ntbs</span>") that is essentially an 
<span style="font-variant:small-caps">ntbs</span> in the ordinary literal encoding.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4981"/>.
</p>

<ol>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[exception]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
virtual const char* what() const noexcept;
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Returns</i>: An implementation-defined <span style="font-variant:small-caps">ntbs</span> 
<ins>in the ordinary literal encoding</ins>.
<p/>
<i>Remarks</i>: The message may be a null-terminated multibyte string (<sref ref="[multibyte.strings]"/>), 
suitable for conversion and display as a <tt>wstring</tt> (<sref ref="[string.classes]"/>, 
<sref ref="[locale.codecvt]"/>). The return value remains valid until the exception object from which it 
is obtained is destroyed or a non-<tt>const</tt> member function of the exception object is called.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
