<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3658" status="New">
<title><tt>basic_streambuf::sputn</tt> is both overspecified and underspecified</title>
<section><sref ref="[streambuf.pub.put]"/></section>
<submitter>Jonathan Wakely</submitter>
<date>17 Jan 2022</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
The specification for <tt>basic_streambuf::sputn</tt> is:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
<i>Returns:</i> <tt>xsputn(s, n)</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
One interpretation of this implies that <tt>sputn</tt> can't insert characters directly into the 
put area if there is space for them, it has to make a virtual call. That has significant overhead 
for repeated calls, such as inserting many small strings/string_views in a loop.
<p/>
But another interpretation is that it doesn't use "<i>Effects:</i> Equivalent to" or anything like 
that, so doesn't say an actual call to <tt>xsputn</tt> happens. Strictly speaking, it only says it 
returns the value that <tt>xsputn</tt> would return, and doesn't even have to produce any of its effects!
<p/>
We should describe the effects, not the return value, and we should do so in a way that does not 
overconstrain the implementation. It should not be necessary to make a virtual call to <tt>xsputn</tt> 
if the put area has capacity for the characters. On the other hand, if it doesn't have capacity, then 
calling <tt>xsputn</tt> is the best option; it allows the derived <tt>streambuf</tt> to decide how 
best to handle large writes.
<p/>
The proposed resolution replaces the <i>Returns:</i> element with an <i>Effects:</i> element, so that 
we specify that those effects actually occur. A normative remark is added to give the implementation 
leeway to avoid the virtual call when it isn't needed.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <paper num="N4901"/>. 
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[streambuf.pub.put]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
streamsize sputn(const char_type* s, streamsize n);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
<ins>-?- <i>Preconditions:</i> <tt>[s, s+n)</tt> is a valid range.</ins>
<p/>
<ins>-?- <i>Effects:</i> <tt>return xsputn(s, n)</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
<ins>-?- <i>Remarks:</i> When <tt>(epptr() - pptr()) &gt;= n</tt>, it is unspecified whether the characters 
are written directly to the output sequence without calling <tt>xsputn</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
-2- <i>Returns:</i> <tt>xsputn(s, n)</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
