<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3367" status="WP">
<title>Integer-class conversions should not throw</title>
<section><sref ref="[iterator.concept.winc]"/></section>
<submitter>Casey Carter</submitter>
<date>07 Jan 2020</date>
<priority>0</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
It's widely established that neither conversions of integral types to <tt>bool</tt> nor conversions 
between different integral types throw exceptions. These properties are crucial to supporting exception 
guarantees in algorithms, containers, and other uses of iterators and their difference types. 
Integer-class types must provide the same guarantees to support the same use cases as do integer types.
</p>

<note>2020-01-14; Daniel comments</note>
<ol>
<li><p>We probably need to think about providing the stronger guarantee that all integer-class operations 
are also <tt>noexcept</tt> in addition to the guarantee that they do not throw any exceptions.</p></li>
<li><p>The fixed wording in LWG <iref ref="3358"/>, <sref ref="[span.cons]"/> p9 depends on the no-throw-guarantee 
of integer-class conversions to integral types.</p></li>
</ol>

<note>2020-01-25 Status set to Tentatively Ready after five positive votes on the reflector.</note>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4842">N4842</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[iterator.concept.winc]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote class="note">
<p>
[<i>Drafting note:</i> There's a bit of drive-by editing here to change occurrences of the meaningless 
"type is convertible to type" to "expression is convertible to type". Paragraph 7 only has drive-by edits. ]
</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
<p>
-6- <del>All</del><ins>Expressions of</ins> integer-class type<del>s</del> are explicitly convertible to 
<del>all</del><ins>any</ins> integral type<del>s and</del><ins>. Expressions of integral type are both</ins>
implicitly and explicitly convertible <del>from all integral types</del><ins>to any integer-class type. 
Conversions between integral and integer-class types do not exit via an exception</ins>.
<p/>
-7- <del>All</del><ins>Expressions <tt><i>E</i></tt> of</ins> integer-class type<del>s</del> <ins><tt>I</tt></ins> 
are contextually convertible to <tt>bool</tt> as if by <tt>bool(<del>a</del><ins><i>E</i></ins> != I(0))</tt><del>, 
where <tt>a</tt> is an instance of the integral-class type <tt>I</tt></del>.
</p>
</blockquote>

</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
