<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2460" status="C++17">
<title>LWG issue 2408 and value categories</title>
<section><sref ref="[meta.trans.other]"/><sref ref="[iterator.traits]"/></section>
<submitter>Richard Smith</submitter>
<date>19 Nov 2014</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
LWG issue <iref ref="2408"/> changes the meat of the specification of <tt>common_type</tt> to compute:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[&hellip;] the type, if any, of an unevaluated conditional expression (5.16) whose first operand is an 
arbitrary value of type <tt>bool</tt>, whose second operand is an <tt>xvalue</tt> of type <tt>T1</tt>, 
and whose third operand is an xvalue of type <tt>T2</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
This has an effect on the specification that I think was unintended. It used to be the case that 
<tt>common_type&lt;T&amp;, U&amp;&amp;&gt;</tt> would consider the type of a conditional between an 
lvalue of type <tt>T</tt> and an xvalue of type <tt>U</tt>. It's now either invalid (because there is 
no such thing as an xvalue of reference type) or considers the type of a conditional between an xvalue 
of type <tt>T</tt> and an xvalue of type <tt>U</tt>, depending on how you choose to read it.
<p/>
Put another way, this has the effect of changing the usual definition from:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
typedef decay_t&lt;decltype(true ? declval&lt;T&gt;() : declval&lt;U&gt;())&gt; type;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
to:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
typedef decay_t&lt;decltype(true ? declval&lt;remove_reference_t&lt;T&gt;&gt;() : declval&lt;remove_reference_t&lt;U&gt;&gt;())&gt; type;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
It also makes <tt>common_type</tt> underspecified in the case where one of the operands is of type <tt>void</tt>; 
in that case, the resulting type depends on whether the expression is a throw-expression, which is not 
specified (but used to be).
<p/>
Also on the subject of this wording: the changes to <sref ref="[iterator.traits]"/> say that 
<tt>iterator_traits&lt;T&gt;</tt> "shall have no members" in some cases. That's wrong. It's a class type; 
it always has at least a copy constructor, a copy assignment operator, and a destructor. Plus this 
removes the usual library liberty to add additional members with names that don't collide with normal 
usage (for instance, if a later version of the standard adds members, they can't be present here as a 
conforming extension). Perhaps this should instead require that the class doesn't have members with any 
of those five names? That's what <iref ref="2408"/> does for <tt>common_type</tt>'s type member.
</p>

<note>2016-08 Chicago</note>
<p>This issue has two parts, one dealing with <tt>common_type</tt>, the other with <tt>iterator_traits</tt>. 
The first of these is resolved by <iref ref="2465"/>.  See below for the proposed resolution for the other one.</p>
<p>Wed PM: Move to Tentatively Ready</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>Change <sref ref="[iterator.traits]"/> p.2:</p>

<p>[&hellip;] as publicly accessible members <del>and no other members</del>:</p>

<p>[&hellip;]</p>

<p>Otherwise, <tt>iterator_traits&lt;Iterator&gt;</tt> shall have no members <ins>by any of the above names</ins>.</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
