<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2820" status="New">
<title>Clarify <tt>&lt;cstdint&gt;</tt> macros</title>
<section><sref ref="[cstdint]"/></section>
<submitter>Thomas Koeppe</submitter>
<date>12 Nov 2016</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
I would like clarification from LWG regarding the various limit macros like <tt>INT_8_MIN</tt> in <tt>&lt;cstdint&gt;</tt>, 
in pursuit of editorial cleanup of this header's synopsis. I have two questions:
</p>
<ol>
<li><p>At present, macros like <tt>INT_8_MIN</tt> that correspond to the optional type <tt>int8_t</tt> are required 
(unconditionally), whereas the underlying type to which they appertain is only optional. Is this deliberate? 
Should the macros also be optional?</p></li>
<li><p>Is it deliberate that C++ only specifies sized aliases for the sizes 8, 16, 32 and 64, whereas the corresponding 
C header allows type aliases and macros for arbitrary sizes for implementations that choose to provide extended integer 
types? Is the C++ wording more restrictive by accident?</p></li>
</ol>

<note>2017-01-27 Telecon</note>
<p>Priority 3</p>

<note>2017-03-04, Kona</note>
<p>C11 ties the macro names to the existence of the types. Marshall to research the second question.</p>
<p>Close <ref iref="2764"/> as a duplicate of this issue.</p>

<note>2017-03-18, Thomas comments and provides wording</note>
<p>
This is as close as I can get to the C wording without resolving part (a) of the issue (whether we deliberately don't 
allow sized type aliases for sizes other than 8, 16, 32, 64, a departure from C). Once we resolve part (a), we need 
to revisit <tt>&lt;cinttypes&gt;</tt> and fix up the synopsis (perhaps to get rid of <tt>N</tt>) and add similar 
wording as the one below to make the formatting macros for the fixed-width types optional. For historical interest,
this issue is related to LWG <iref ref="553"/> and LWG <iref ref="841"/>.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
This wording is relative to <a href="http://wg21.link/n4640">N4640</a>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Append the following content to <sref ref="[cstdint.syn]"/> p2:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-2- The header defines all types and macros the same as the C standard library header <tt>&lt;stdint.h&gt;</tt>.
<ins>In particular, for each of the fixed-width types (<tt>int8_t</tt>, <tt>int16_t</tt>, <tt>int32_t</tt>, 
<tt>int64_t</tt>, <tt>uint8_t</tt>, <tt>uint16_t</tt>, <tt>uint32_t</tt>, <tt>uint64_t</tt>) the type alias and 
the corresponding limit macros are defined if and only if the implementation provides the corresponding type.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
