<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3577" status="New">
<title>Merging an (unordered) associative container with itself</title>
<section><sref ref="[associative.reqmts.general]"/><sref ref="[unord.req.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Joaqu&iacute;n M L&oacute;pez Mu&ntilde;oz</submitter>
<date>04 Aug 2021</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
For the expression <tt>a.merge(a2)</tt>, it is not explicitly stated whether <tt>a2</tt> can be the 
same object as <tt>a</tt>. libstdc++-v3 and libc++ seemingly assume this is not allowed, as the following code
produces an infinite loop with both standard library implementations:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;set&gt;

int main()
{
  std::multiset&lt;int&gt; c={0, 0};
  c.merge(c);
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
A strict reading of postconditions seems to ban the case where <tt>a</tt> and <tt>a2</tt> are the same:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p><sref ref="[associative.reqmts.general]"/>: "Iterators referring to the transferred elements [&hellip;] 
now behave as iterators into <tt>a</tt>, not into <tt>a2</tt>": if <tt>a</tt> and <tt>a2</tt> are the same, 
a transferred iterator can't be both an iterator to <tt>a</tt> and not an iterator to <tt>a2</tt>.</p></li>
<li><p><sref ref="[unord.req.general]"/>: "Iterators referring to the transferred elements and all iterators 
referring to <tt>a</tt> will be invalidated, but iterators to elements remaining in <tt>a2</tt> will remain valid": 
if <tt>a</tt> and <tt>a2</tt> are the same, an iterator can't both be invalidated and remain valid.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>
Even if a provision is made that, when <tt>a</tt> and <tt>a2</tt> are the same, no elements are transferred by 
convention, <sref ref="[unord.req.general]"/> would still implicitly ban the case, as all iterators would be 
invalidated but the iterators to the remaining elements (again, all iterators) would remain valid, which is 
contradictory.
<p/>
For context, analogous operations for <tt>std::list</tt> take inconsistent approaches:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p><tt>splice(const_iterator position, list&amp; x)</tt> requires that source and destination be not the same.</p></li>
<li><p><tt>splice(const_iterator position, list&amp; x, const_iterator i)</tt> implicitly allows <tt>addressof(x) == this</tt>, 
as the case <tt>position == i</tt> is taken care of.</p></li>
<li><p><tt>std::list::merge</tt> explicitly allows the case <tt>addressof(x) == this</tt> (resulting in a no-op).</p></li>
</ul>

<note>2021-08-20; Reflector poll</note>
<p>
Set priority to 3 after reflector poll.

Tim Song commented:
"I think the current PR of LWG<iref ref="2414"/> bans this code,
but we might want to have consistency with <code>list::merge</code> instead."
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
