<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2368" status="Resolved">
<title>Replacing global <tt>operator new</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[new.delete]"/></section>
<submitter>Stephen Clamage</submitter>
<date>20 Feb 2014</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
Section <sref ref="[new.delete]"/> and subsections shows:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
void* operator new(std::size_t size);
void* operator new[](std::size_t size);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
That is, without exception-specifications. (Recall that C++03 specified these functions with <tt>throw(std::bad_alloc)</tt>.)
<p/>
Section <sref ref="[res.on.exception.handling]"/> the end of paragraph 4 says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
Any other functions defined in the C++ standard library that do not have an exception-specification may throw implementation-defined 
exceptions unless otherwise specified. An implementation may strengthen this implicit exception-specification by adding an explicit one.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
For example, an implementation could provide C++03-compatible declarations of <tt>operator new</tt>.
<p/>
Programmers are allowed to replace these <tt>operator new</tt> functions. But how can you write the definition of these functions when 
the exception specification can vary among implementations? For example, the declarations
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
void* operator new(std::size_t size) throw(std::bad_alloc);
void* operator new(std::size_t size);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
are not compatible.
<p/>
From what I have been able to determine, gcc has a hack for the special case of <tt>operator new</tt> to ignore the differences in 
(at least) the two cases I show above. But can users expect all compilers to quietly ignore the incompatibility?
<p/>
The blanket permission to add any explicit exception specification could cause a problem for any user-overridable function. 
Different implementations could provide incompatible specifications, making portable code impossible to write.
</p>

<note>2016-03, Jacksonville</note>
<p>
STL: Core changes to remove dynamic exception specs would make this moot<br/>
Room: This is on track to be resolved by <a href="https://wg21.link/P0003">P0003</a>, or may be moot.<br/>
</p>

<note>2016-07, Toronto Thursday night issues processing</note>
<p>Resolved by <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2016/p0003r5.html">P0003</a>.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
