<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2491" status="New">
<title><tt>std::less&lt;T*&gt;</tt> in constant expression</title>
<section><sref ref="[comparisons]"/></section>
<submitter>Agust&iacute;n K-ballo Berg&eacute;</submitter>
<date>1 Apr 2015</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
It is not entirely clear if and when the specializations of <tt>std::less</tt> (and friends) for pointer types 
can be used in a constant expression. Consider the following code:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;functional&gt;

struct foo {};
foo x, y;
constexpr bool b = std::less&lt;foo*&gt;{}(&amp;x, &amp;y); // [1]

foo z[] = {{}, {}};
constexpr bool ba = std::less&lt;foo*&gt;{}(&amp;z[0], &amp;z[1]); // [2]
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
Comparing the address of unrelated objects is not a constant expression since the result is unspecified, so 
it could be expected for [1] to fail and [2] to succeed. However, <tt>std::less</tt> specialization for pointer 
types is well-defined and yields a total order, so it could just as well be expected for [1] to succeed. Finally, 
since the implementation of such specializations is not mandated, [2] could fail as well (This could happen, if
an implementation would provide such a specialization and if that would use built-in functions that would not be
allowed in constant expressions, for example). In any case, the standard should be clear so as to avoid 
implementation-defined <tt>constexpr</tt>-ness.
</p>

<note>2017-01-22, Jens provides rationale and proposed wording</note>
<p>
<tt>std::less&lt;T*&gt;</tt> is required to deliver a total order on pointers.
However, the layout of global objects is typically determined
by the linker, not the compiler, so requiring <tt>std::less&lt;T*&gt;</tt> to
provide an ordering at compile-time that is consistent with
run-time would need results from linking to feed back to
the compiler, something that C++ has traditionally not required.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4618">N4618</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Add at the end of <sref ref="[comparisons]"/>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
-2- For templates <tt>less</tt>, <tt>greater</tt>, <tt>less_equal</tt>, and <tt>greater_equal</tt>, [&hellip;], 
if the call operator calls a built-in operator comparing pointers, the call operator yields a strict total order 
that is consistent among those specializations and is also consistent with the partial order imposed by those 
built-in operators. <ins>Relational comparisons of pointer values are not required to be usable as constant expressions.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
