<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3522" status="WP">
<title>Missing requirement on <tt>InputIterator</tt> template parameter for <tt>priority_queue</tt> constructors</title>
<section><sref ref="[priority.queue]"/></section>
<submitter>Tim Song</submitter>
<date>17 Feb 2021</date>
<priority>99</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
There is nothing in <sref ref="[priority.queue]"/> or more generally <sref ref="[container.adaptors]"/>
saying that <tt>InputIterator</tt> in the following constructor templates has to be an input iterator.
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;class InputIterator&gt;
    priority_queue(InputIterator first, InputIterator last, const Compare&amp; x,
                    const Container&amp;);
template&lt;class InputIterator&gt;
    priority_queue(InputIterator first, InputIterator last,
                    const Compare&amp; x = Compare(), Container&amp;&amp; = Container());
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
The second constructor template above therefore accepts
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
std::priority_queue&lt;int&gt; x = {1, 2};
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
to produce a <tt>priority_queue</tt> that contains a single element <tt>2</tt>. This behavior seems extremely questionable.
</p>

<note>2021-02-26; LWG telecon</note>
<p>
Set status to Tentatively Ready after discussion and poll.
<table>
<tr><th>F</th><th>A</th><th>N</th></tr>
<tr><td>11</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr>
</table>
</p>

<note>2021-06-07 Approved at June 2021 virtual plenary. Status changed: Voting &rarr; WP.</note>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<blockquote class="note">
<p>
[<i>Drafting note</i>: Because <a href="https://wg21.link/P1425">an upcoming paper</a>
provides iterator-pair constructors for other container adaptors, the wording below
adds the restriction to <sref ref="[container.adaptors.general]"/> so that it also
covers the constructors that will be added by that paper.
&mdash; <i>end drafting note</i>]
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4878">N4878</a>.
</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Add the following paragraph to <sref ref="[container.adaptors.general]"/> after p3:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<ins>-?- A constructor template of a container adaptor shall not participate in
overload resolution if it has an <tt>InputIterator</tt> template parameter and a
type that does not qualify as an input iterator is deduced for that parameter.</ins>
</p>
<p>
-4- A deduction guide for a container adaptor shall not participate in overload resolution if any of the following are true:
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: none">
<li><p>(4.1) &mdash; It has an <tt>InputIterator</tt> template parameter and a type that does not qualify as an input iterator is deduced for that parameter.</p></li>
<li><p>[&hellip;]</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
