<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2892" status="NAD">
<title>Relax the prohibition on libraries adding <tt>constexpr</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[constexpr.functions]"/></section>
<submitter>Great Britain</submitter>
<date>3 Feb 2017</date>
<priority>1</priority>

<discussion>
<b>Addresses GB 38</b>

<p>Relax the prohibition on libraries adding <tt>constexpr</tt>; this was a constraint requested by library implementers when 
<tt>constexpr</tt> was new, and those same implementers now feel unduly constrained.</p>
<p>Proposed change: Rewrite the whole sub-clause to support libraries adding <tt>constexpr</tt> in a compatible manner, 
much like the freedom to add a <tt>noexcept</tt> specification.</p>

<note>2017-02-20, Marshall adds wording</note>
<p>The simplest change would be to strike the sentence "An implementation shall not [&hellip;] explicitly required". However, 
people seem to want a definite permission here, so I have provided one.</p>

<note>2017-07 Toronto Thurs Issue Prioritization</note>
<p>Priority 1</p>

<note>2018-06 Rapperswil Thursday issues processing</note>
<p>This is a feature request; not a defect. We've had two cross-group meetings over this, and there is no consensus for changing this. Closing as NAD.</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4640">N4640</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[constexpr.functions]"/> as indicated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This International Standard explicitly requires that certain standard library functions are constexpr (7.1.5). <ins>An 
implementation may declare additional standard library function signatures as constexpr</ins><del>An implementation shall 
not declare any standard library function signature as constexpr except for those where it is explicitly required</del>. 
Within any header that provides any non-defining declarations of constexpr functions or constructors an implementation 
shall provide corresponding definitions.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
