<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3054" status="WP">
<title><tt>uninitialized_copy</tt> appears to not be able to meet its exception-safety guarantee</title>
<section><sref ref="[uninitialized.copy]"/></section>
<submitter>Jon Cohen</submitter>
<date>24 Jan 2018</date>
<priority>2</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
I believe that <tt>uninitialized_copy</tt> is unable to meet its exception-safety guarantee in the
presence of throwing move constructors:
<p/>
<sref ref="[specialized.algorithms]"/>/1 has two statements of note for the specialized algorithms such
as <tt>uninitialized_copy</tt>:
<p/>
<ul>
<li><p>the provided iterators satisfy the <tt>InputIterator</tt> requirements (<sref ref="[input.iterators]"/>)</p></li>
<li><p>if an exception is thrown during the algorithm then there are no effects</p></li>
</ul>
<p/>
Suppose we have an input iterator <tt>Iter</tt>. Then <tt>std::move_iterator&lt;Iter&gt;</tt> appears
to also be an input iterator. Notably, it still satisfies that <tt>(void)*a, *a</tt> is equivalent to
<tt>*a</tt> for move iterator <tt>a</tt> since the dereference only forms an rvalue reference, it
doesn't actually perform the move operation (<sref ref="[input.iterators]"/> Table 95 &mdash; "Input iterator requirements").
<p/>
Suppose also that we have a type <tt>T</tt> whose move constructor can throw, a range of <tt>T</tt>'s
<tt>[t<sub>begin</sub>, t<sub>end</sub>)</tt>, and a pointer to an uninitialized buffer of <tt>T</tt>'s
<tt>buf</tt>. Then <tt>std::uninitialized_copy(std::make_move_iterator(t<sub>begin</sub>),
std::make_move_iterator(t<sub>end</sub>), buf)</tt> can't possibly satisfy the property that it has
no effects if one of the moves throws &mdash; we'll have a <tt>T</tt> left in a moved-from state with
no way of recovering.
<p/>
See <a href="https://wandbox.org/permlink/aYdtwlPckvXp59eJ">here</a> for an example in code.
<p/>
It seems like the correct specification for <tt>uninitialized_copy</tt> should be that if
<tt>InputIterator</tt>'s <tt>operator*</tt> returns an rvalue reference and
<tt>InputIterator::value_type</tt>'s move constructor is not marked <tt>noexcept</tt>, then
<tt>uninitialized_copy</tt> will leave the objects in the underlying range in a valid but
unspecified state.
</p>

<note>2018-01-24, Casey comments and provides wording</note>
<p>
This issue points out a particular hole in the "..if an exception is thrown in the following algorithms
there are no effects." wording for the "uninitialized" memory algorithms
(<sref ref="[specialized.algorithms]"/>/1) and suggests a PR to patch over said hole. The true problem
here is that "no effects" is not and never has been implementable. For example, "<tt>first != last</tt>"
may have observable effects that an implementation is required to somehow reverse if some later operation
throws an exception.
<p/>
Rather than finding problem case after problem case and applying individual patches, we should fix the
root cause. If we alter the problematic sentence from [specialized.algorithms]/1 we can fix the issue
once and for all and have implementable algorithms.
</p>

<note>2018-02-05, Priority set to 2 after mailing list discussion</note>

<note>2018-06 Rapperswil Thursday issues processing</note>
<p>Status to Ready</p>
<note>2018-11, Adopted in San Diego</note>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="https://wg21.link/n4713">N4713</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[specialized.algorithms]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-1- [&hellip;]
<p/>
Unless otherwise specified, if an exception is thrown in the following algorithms <ins>objects
constructed by a placement <i>new-expression</i> (<sref ref="[expr.new]"/>) are destroyed in an
unspecified order before allowing the exception to propagate</ins><del>there are no effects</del>.
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[uninitialized.move]"/> as indicated (The removed paragraphs are now
unnecessary):</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
template&lt;class InputIterator, class ForwardIterator&gt;
  ForwardIterator uninitialized_move(InputIterator first, InputIterator last,
                                     ForwardIterator result);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
<del>-2- <i>Remarks:</i> If an exception is thrown, some objects in the range <tt>[first, last)</tt>
are left in a valid but unspecified state.</del>
</p>
</blockquote>
<pre>
template&lt;class InputIterator, class Size, class ForwardIterator&gt;
  pair&lt;InputIterator, ForwardIterator&gt;
    uninitialized_move_n(InputIterator first, Size n, ForwardIterator result);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
<del>-4- <i>Remarks:</i> If an exception is thrown, some objects in the range <tt>[first,
std::next(first, n))</tt> are left in a valid but unspecified state.</del>
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
