<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="2477" status="C++17">
<title>Inconsistency of wordings in <tt>std::vector::erase()</tt> and <tt>std::deque::erase()</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[deque.modifiers]"/><sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/></section>
<submitter>Anton Savin</submitter>
<date>3 Mar 2015</date>
<priority>0</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
In the latest draft N4296, and in all drafts up to at least N3337:
<p/>
<sref ref="[deque.modifiers]"/>/5 (regarding <tt>deque::erase()</tt>):
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Complexity</i>: The number of calls to the destructor is the same as the number of elements erased, but
the number of calls to the <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bold">assignment operator</span> is no more 
than the lesser of the number of elements before the erased elements and the number of elements after the erased elements.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/4 (regarding <tt>vector::erase()</tt>):
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<i>Complexity</i>: The destructor of <tt>T</tt> is called the number of times equal to the number of the elements
erased, but the <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bold">move assignment operator</span> of <tt>T</tt> is called 
the number of times equal to the number of elements in the vector after the erased elements.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
Is there any reason for explicit mentioning of move assignment for <tt>std::vector::erase()</tt>? 
Shouldn't these two wordings be the same with this regard?
<p/>
Also, for <tt>std::deque</tt>, it's not clear from the text which destructors and assignment operators are called.
</p>

<note>2015-05, Lenexa</note>
<p>
Move to Immediate.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N4296.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Change <sref ref="[deque.modifiers]"/>/5 to:</p>

<p>
-5- <i>Complexity</i>: The number of calls to the destructor <ins>of <tt>T</tt></ins> is the same as the number of 
elements erased, but the number of calls to the assignment operator <ins>of <tt>T</tt></ins> is no more than the 
lesser of the number of elements before the erased elements and the number of elements after the erased elements.
</p>
</li>

<li><p>Change <sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/4 to:</p>

<p>
-4- <i>Complexity</i>: The destructor of <tt>T</tt> is called the number of times equal to the number of the elements
erased, but the <del>move</del> assignment operator of <tt>T</tt> is called the number of times equal to the number of
elements in the vector after the erased elements.
</p>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
