<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd">

<issue num="3271" status="NAD">
<title>Parsing functions should save and restore stream format state</title>
<section><sref ref="[time.parse]"/></section>
<submitter>Howard Hinnant</submitter>
<date>2 Sep 2019</date>
<priority>3</priority>

<discussion>
<p>
<tt>from_stream</tt> overloads may need to set various formatting state and flags of the <tt>basic_istream</tt> 
to implement the parsing functionality. Such settings must not persist beyond the parsing functions. Thus 
these functions need to save and restore any settings on the <tt>basic_istream</tt> they may need to change.
</p>

<note>2019-10 Priority set to 3 after reflector discussion</note>

<note>2020-02, Prague; Close as NAD</note>

LWG reviewed the issue and decided no change is needed.
Unless specified to change the flags, it's assumed that the stream flags are
unchanged by any input function.
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to <a href="http://wg21.link/n4830">N4830</a>.</p>

<blockquote class="note">
<p>
[<i>Drafting note:</i> The modification of <sref ref="[time.parse]"/> p1 is intended to be non-conflictingly 
mergeable with the change suggested by LWG <iref ref="3269"/> at the same paragraph.]
</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[time.parse]"/> as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p> 
-1- Each parse overload specified in this subclause calls <tt>from_stream</tt> unqualified, 
so as to enable argument dependent lookup (<sref ref="[basic.lookup.argdep]"/>).
<ins>In the following paragraphs, let <tt>is</tt> denote an object of type 
<tt>basic_istream&lt;charT, traits&gt;</tt>, where <tt>charT</tt> and
<tt>traits</tt> are template parameters in that context.</ins>
<p/>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
-10- All <tt>from_stream</tt> overloads behave as unformatted input functions, except that they have an 
unspecified effect on the value returned by subsequent calls to <tt>basic_istream&lt;&gt;::gcount()</tt>.
<ins>Any changes made to <tt>is.fill()</tt>, <tt>is.width()</tt> or <tt>is.flags()</tt> are undone 
prior to an returning or exceptional execution ([thread.once.callonce]).</ins> 
Each overload takes a format string containing ordinary characters and flags which have special meaning. 
Each flag begins with a <tt>%</tt>. Some flags can be modified by <tt>E</tt> or <tt>O</tt>. During parsing 
each flag interprets characters as parts of date and time types according to Table [tab:time.parse.spec]. 
Some flags can be modified by a width parameter given as a positive decimal integer called out as 
<tt><i>N</i></tt> below which governs how many characters are parsed from the stream in interpreting the 
flag. All characters in the format string that are not represented in Table [tab:time.parse.spec], except 
for white space, are parsed unchanged from the stream. A white space character matches zero or more white
space characters in the input stream.
</p>
</blockquote>

</li>
</ol>

</resolution>
</issue>
